<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse or historie of bees Shewing their nature and usage, and the great profit of them. VVhereunto is added the causes, and cure of blasted wheat. And some remedies for blasted hops, and rie, and fruit. Together with the causes of smutty wheat: all which are very usefull for this later age. Written by Richard Remnant.</title>
            <author>Remnant, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1637</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10606</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20879</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105189</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840918</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840918</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5462</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10606)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5462)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 934:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse or historie of bees Shewing their nature and usage, and the great profit of them. VVhereunto is added the causes, and cure of blasted wheat. And some remedies for blasted hops, and rie, and fruit. Together with the causes of smutty wheat: all which are very usefull for this later age. Written by Richard Remnant.</title>
                  <author>Remnant, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 47, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Young for Thomas Slater, dwelling in duck lane at the white Swan,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1637.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Library of Congress.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bees --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Wheat --  Diseases and pests --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5462:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5462:1"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE OR HISTORIE OF BEES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>SHEWING</hi> Their Nature and uſage, and the great profit of them.</p>
            <p>VVhereunto is added the cauſes, and cure of blaſted Wheat.</p>
            <p>And ſome remedies for blaſted Hops, and Rie, and Fruit.</p>
            <p>Together with the cauſes of ſmutty Wheat: All which are very uſefull for this later age.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by</hi> RICHARD REMNANT.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Robert Young</hi> for <hi>Thomas Slater,</hi> dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in duck lane at the white Swan. 1637.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:5462:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5462:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Earing and reading the Diſcourſes and Writings of very many about Bees, and finding moſt of my Countrymen not over skilfull in the way of keeping and meanes of preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them; as alſo of the way of preſerving wheat, and other things from blaſting by mildews: I having of late had a little leaſure to write, and conſidering the great good and benefite that may bee made of this knowledge; have therefore (though rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) penned this little Treatiſe, for the benefit of preſent and future ages: and am willing alſo, if this prove profitable and acceptable, to add ſomething more hereunto of further uſe. And ſo praying God to give a bleſsing, I reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in the Lord,</hi> RICHARD REMNANT.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:5462:3"/>
            <list>
               <head>The Contents of the firſt Booke.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 1.</hi> OF the nature of Bees. <hi>Folio. 1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 2.</hi> How Bees are bred. <hi>Folio. 2.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 3.</hi> Of their work. <hi>Folio. 9.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 4.</hi> Of the getting of Bees, and how to finde and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy the loſſe of the Queen. <hi>Folio. 13.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 5.</hi> Of the time to remove Bees, and placing them to the beſt advantage. <hi>Folio. 15.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 6.</hi> How to defend your Bees, and preſerve them from their enemies. <hi>Folio. 18.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 7.</hi> Of ſwarmes and ſwarming. Alſo in this chapter is ſhewed how to feed Bees: Alſo how and when to drive full and fat ſtocks. <hi>Folio. 22.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 8.</hi> How to chuſe and know the beſt Hives for ſtore: Alſo how to help them that have too much, or too little food: Thirdly, ſignes of the firſt ſwarming: Fourthly, how to recover Bees that are chilled with cold. <hi>Folio. 31.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 9.</hi> How to make hony, mead, and wax. <hi>Folio. 34.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 10.</hi> Bees and women compared. <hi>Folio. 39.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The Second Booke.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 1.</hi> OF the cauſe and cure of blaſted wheat. <hi>folio. 40.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 2.</hi> How this knowledge come to bee ſo long hid, and now diſcovered. <hi>folio. 43.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter. 3.</hi> The cauſe of ſmutty wheat, with the beſt remedy that I can adviſe you. <hi>folio. 44.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="book">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:5462:3"/>
            <head>A HISTORIE, OR DISCOURSE <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 1.</hi> Of the nature of Bees.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not my purpoſe here, either to follow or to confute other mens opinions concerning Bees: I ſhall briefly ſet down my owne know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in this ſubject.</p>
               <p>To reveale the whole nature of Bees is very hard, and to little pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; at leaſt no great uſe or benefit if it were done: I purpoſe therefore to diſcover onely ſo much as may ſerve for common uſe among us: And firſt of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Bees. They are of nature very hot and fiery;<note place="margin">The nature of Bees.</note>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:5462:4"/>
whence it is that the hony which they gather is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe hot, though extracted out of cold and mild flowers. They are blowne by the females: Their ſex is male and female: They are an entire female Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie, having the males among them but one part of the yeere: Their Queen hath her guard, which depart not from her, which (together with their admirable order, and induſtry) doe repreſent a well governed Common-weale.</p>
               <p>There is but one ſort of good or uſefull Bees in our Country, having ſix legges, foure wings, two fangs, one beake or bill, few intralls, five ſenſes, very quicke and apt for uſe: all of one colour and forme, but differ in quantitie, ſex, beauty, quality, employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and labour, care and providence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 2.</hi> How Bees are bred.</head>
               <p>THe breeding of Bees is after this manner: The fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>males doe blow their brood in the cells or holes of their combs. In the uppermoſt part of their combs they lay up and keepe honey for their winter pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion; in the lower part they breed during all the warme moneths; the firſt and laſt of the yeere they breed females, the ſecond or third courſe is males and females, if the ſtocke be good and forward to ſwarme, elſe they breed no males till the middle part of the yeere: for till they have uſe of males they breed them not. For they know when they blow males, and when females; which I prove thus. Firſt, becauſe they never
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:5462:4"/>
blow males till they have need of them. Secondly, it is apparent by this reaſon, becauſe they place them altogether in the middle of their brood, and the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>males round about them, and make the cells or holes in which they blow them either higher or lower, fit for the body of the ſex which they blow. When they blow males they encreaſe it higher, and when females they gnaw it downe lower,<note place="margin">A ſtrange in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct.</note> as any that will obſerve the worke may ſee. Wherein we may note a ſtrange inſtinct beyond other creatures, in that they know when they breed males, and when females, and when to breed each: which is indeed wonderfull, as alſo many other things in the their common-wealth are: as, their government, and the manner of it; their comely order and valour, their labour and daintie worke, their care and providence. All which are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the beholding and conſideration of all people, both rulers and ſubjects: and I wiſh that good uſe might be made of all the viſible workes of the Lord, I meane the admirable workes of creation and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: for the workes of the Lord are wonderfull, and, I am ſure, ought to be ſought out of all that feare him.</p>
               <p>But to returne whence I digreſt. That there bee males and females I ſhall now ſhew you. There are viſibly to bee obſerved two ſorts among them, the one bigger, the other leſſer: the bigger, which wee call Drones, are indeed the male Bees; they worke not, but live on the labour of the reſt: whence it is that wee give that name Drone,<note place="margin">Reaſons to ſhew that the leſſer Bees are the females.</note> to our unprofitable lubbers in the common-wealth. That the leſſer Bees are the females, I thus prove: It is the female that beares the ſeed in her body, but the leſſer Bee beares
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:5462:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the ſeed in her body and blowes it, therefore they are the females. A ſecond reaſon is this: There is not one male or Drone in the ſtock all the winter (which I will anon prove) therefore the leſſer Bees (being onely there) muſt of neceſſity bee the females: and they blow or breed when the males or Drones are not among them, which proves them to be females. Yet all the ſummer the males are among the females; and are by the females bred for generation, and kept for that uſe: But they kill them for neceſſity; for the males are exceeding great eaters and waſters of the winter proviſion, therefore the females kill them, and had rather be without their ſweet companie, than ſtarve in their winter. I call it their winter when they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not gather food, which is their meanes to maintaine life: for ſo ſoone as ever the hony gathering failes in the fields, the females kill the Drones or males, or drive them out<note n="*" place="margin">Ignavum fucos pecus à praeſepibus ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent.</note>, and ſuffer none in winter.</p>
               <p>Now whereas ſome ſtockes have ſo many Drones that the female Bees are long in killing them, and ſo ſpend their precious time about that, when as they would bee otherwiſe employed: And whereas other ſtocks are ſo weake and poore, that they are not able to kill them; therefore I adviſe you at that time of the yeere to helpe your Bees in killing them: which you may doe in this manner.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">When and how to kill Drones.</note>In the heat of the day in Auguſt (which is the uſuall time when hony-gathering begins to faile) then ſtand at the mouth of your Hives that are full of Drones, and as they come out, bruiſe ſome of them with your fingers on the ſtocks-mouth, and make the hony come forth of them, and leave them among the females; and ſo will they ſucke the hony out of them,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:5462:5"/>
and fall to doe it themſelves, and kill their Drones.</p>
               <p>But for the helpe of them that have many Drones,<note place="margin">Drone-pots: Set theſe pots, and ſtop them cloſe to the Hive mouth, in the heat of the day.</note> and are weake or few themſelves, and ſo cannot ſo well doe it, for them provide drone-pots to doe it: which pots are made of Oſiars, the twigges being ſet ſo cloſe that the Drones cannot get out, and yet wide enough for the females or Queen to goe through. But becauſe the catching in theſe pots doth trouble the Bees, therefore I eſteeme it the better way, if you dare, to kill them with your fingers.</p>
               <p>Concerning the matter in which they blow or breed,<note place="margin">The matter in which they blow.</note> it is ſomething that they gather of the flowers or plants, and bring home, and put it into the holes or cells of their combs, and mixe it finely with a little water, and then blow in it a ſmall thing, leſſe than, or as little as a flie-blote, which comes to be as big as a great Maggot, and coloureth browne; and within eighteen or twenty one dayes, as the weather is colder or hotter, they come forth. Note,<note place="margin">Heat brings forth in eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen or twenty one daies.</note> that it is the heat of the Bees that brings the blote to maturitie, as hens or fowles doe egges: and herein the male hath his uſe alſo, for he is very hot. The place (as I told you) of blowing the males, is in the midſt of the combs and in ſmall number, the females round about them, in exceeding greater number, and the Queens on the edges of the combs, in the midſt and ſafeſt place of the Hive. The males cell is bigger than the females, and the Queenes cell bigger than the common Bees, and farre thicker and ſtronger: and but five, ſix or ſeven in an Hive.</p>
               <p>Whether the Queenes blow the Queenes I am not very certaine, but I take it to be ſo,<note place="margin">Queenes blow Queenes.</note> becauſe of the faireneſſe and excellency of the creature, and the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:5462:6"/>
that is betweene her and the common Bees. But that there is any odds, excellency, or uſe of the males one above another, I find not: neither is there any other uſe of the males but for generation, and breeding, and helping to bring the brood to maturity: and they are great eaters, and labour not, but play and ſport in and out, and take the aire when it is warme, for their pleaſure, and ſo cleanſe their bodies, and back againe to eate and ſleep: a dainty life, from which good Lord deliver me.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The manner of convaying ſeed.</note>The females receive ſeed from the Drones in Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time, after what manner I cannot well tell: But there is in the hinder part of the male or Drone a little white thing like the inſtrument of generation; take one of them alive and cruſh the body of it ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what hard between your fingers, and you ſhall ſee it put forth. Alſo the females have neere their ſtings a little neat place of receit for generation: but whether they receive the ſeed at the head or taile, I am not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine; but if at the taile, the females muſt needs hold their ſtings very cloſe: for if the males were prickt or venomed thereby, common ſenſe (without reaſon) would make them take heed of comming there againe; which many reaſonable creatures (the more ſhame for them) cannot doe.</p>
               <p>The Queen, being a female, hath a ſting in her taile, but uſeth it not,<note place="margin">The beauty and uſe of the Queene.</note> it being onely for diſtinction of ſex and ornament. She is longer and ſomthing bigger than a common Bee, much clearer and more beautifull, and yellower under the belly and the legges. She rules and governes all by commanders, and in working time goeth from place to place in the Hive: ſhe hath a ſpeciall guard about her of the faireſt and moſt valo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:5462:6"/>
Bees, which alway attend her within and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, eſpecially when ſhee comes abroad. And in ſwarming time you may in the heat of the day ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſee her. For a little before they ſwarme ſhe will come abroad, and flie about to take the aire, and make her ſelfe fit to goe with the ſwarme, and to harden her ſelfe: for ſhe is very tender and chilly,<note place="margin">The Queen is very choiſe and chilly, and ſoone loſt, which done ruines the common-wealth.</note> by reaſon ſhe comes ſeldome abroad. There is one of them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies in the Hive, both winter and ſummer; and but one onely, except it bee in ſwarming time: For more than one the Commons will not endure, and without one they cannot ſubſiſt, but are diſtract, diſperſt, wander and worke not, but come to nought and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh; which is worthy our obſervation, and may be holpen, as I will ſhew hereafter.</p>
               <p>Furthermore the Queenes are the calling Bees, and are bred to goe forth one with every ſwarme: and if two goe in a ſwarme, then will there be a combuſtion among the commons, and one will kill another, ſtriving which of thoſe Queenes ſhall governe; and ſo will fight till one of thoſe Queene be killed: which done, they will bee all quiet and fall to worke. This is worth the noting; Therefore to remedy it,<note place="margin">How to make peace when there is vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance about the Queene.</note> I take away one of the Queenes from ſuch a ſwarme, and put her into the old ſtocke againe: for ſometimes all the Queenes goe away with the ſwarmes, and then the old ſtocke will periſh.</p>
               <p>Now in ſwarming time, when they firſt begin to ſwarme, there are 5, 6, or 7. Queen-Bees, more or leſſe, as they are prepared for ſwarming, and they are all calling Bees: and after the firſt ſwarme about ten dayes they call for a ſecond: and ſo continue in calling till they have done caſting.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:5462:7"/>
                  <note place="margin">When they call.</note>Between the firſt and ſecond ſwarmes, commonly they ſtay twelve or foureteene dayes, but for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and third, but a day or two, if the weather hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der not.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Calling Bees.</note>The Queenes have ſeverall notes, and call out one bigger, another leſſer, one note under another; And I thinke can alter their notes as they liſt; for the leſſer noted Bee calls laſt, and is moſt ſhrill and earneſt, and goeth away with the ſecond ſwarme: as once I found, when I had a ſwarme went out and came home a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and went into the next ſtock. And there the ſmaller noted Bee, called a day or two, till the ſwarm came away againe: And the ſmaller note being gone in the ſecond ſwarme, then the next ſmall note doth alter, and calleth as ſhrill and loud as the former.</p>
               <p>Theſe Queenes goe calling round about, and over all the ſtock (as you may heare in an evening.) And they reſt not till the ſwarmes are ſet forth: and if there be more Queenes bred than to furniſh every ſwarme with one, then ſo ſoone as the ſtock hath done ſwarming, they kill all thoſe Queenes ſave one, and bring them out of the Hive.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Queens are gentle, amiable, very loving.</note>The Queen is a very gentle and loving Bee, and will not ſting: And if you chance to reſcue her from danger, or ſuccour her any way (as I have often done) then will ſhe flie to you, and hang about you, and not willingly depart from you, which is worth your noting and obſervation.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Looke care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully after the Queene in ſwarming time, but trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble not the ſwarme.</note>Now in time of ſwarming, it behoves you careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to looke after your Queene Bee: for ſhe is often beaten downe, or falleth among the weedes, beanes, or graſſe, or ſuch like, neare the ſwarme; which if you doe not eſpie and helpe, all the ſwarme will returne
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:5462:7"/>
home againe: and then it is a chance if ever they come forth againe. Which you may prevent, by looking diligently for the Queen; who is eaſily found, becauſe whereſoever ſhe is, there the guard will ſit faſt about her; who are a knot or clump of Bees as big as a Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisball, or ſomewhat bigger, according as the ſwarme is in quantitie. Therefore in ſwarming time you muſt looke about diligently neere the Bees, and if you find her fallen at the mouth of the Hive, or elſewhere, take her up and put her to the ſwarme.</p>
               <p>The Queenes lie moſt commonly in the middle of the ſwarme, and are ſafely guarded, and carefully at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended: a thing worthy obſervation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 3.</hi> Concerning their Worke.</head>
               <p>THe common Bees, (as I ſaid before) they are fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>males, and are bred in farre greater number than the other. For they are the working Bees: and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them are loſt in foule weather. Alſo they have many enemies, and ſo periſh by them. Theſe are they that fight for, and defend the reſt: and ſo are in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Beſides, they are the firſt that endure penury: for they ſpare their food (when it begins to be ſcarce) to maintaine their Queene:<note place="margin">In cold wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther keepe the Hive cloſe in breeding time.</note> alſo they are often chil'd in the brood; therefore in breeding time, when the weather is cold, it is good to keep the mouth of your Hive ſomewhat cloſe, but eſpecially in the night: and keepe the Hives warme.</p>
               <p>Alſo you muſt endevour to kill and deſtroy all their enemies, to prevent all dangers, to cure all diſeaſes,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:5462:8"/>
to cleanſe them in the ſpring time, and to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate them with neceſſaries as you can; which to doe I ſhall ſhew hereafter.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Their curious worke.</note>Concerning the manner of their working, it is very daintie, curious and exact: their combs placed ſo, as they may paſſe between them, and come at every cell or hole to lay up hony or to breed in: And alway in warme weather, they cleanſe and repaire their worke, and in cold weather, they lie or ſit there cloſe together, to keepe themſelves warme. They gather wax all the yeere, from the firſt gathering to the laſt, from the willow to the blowing Ivie: but they gather their hony in warme moneths, except it be cold and dry; and when the hony dewes fall, they gather abundantly.<note place="margin">The manner of their gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring hony and wax.</note> They take up or draw the hony with a fine little beake like a Gnat, and carry it home in a little bladder, or thing like the crap of a bird or hen, in the forepart of their bodies, and lay it up in their cells or holes, and cover it over finely with thin wax, and ſo keepe it for proviſion.</p>
               <p>The hony, when it is firſt extracted or drawne, is as thin as any rock water: but by the heat of the Bees, and age, it becommeth thicke and hard. The wax is gathered of the flowers or bloomes, with the fangs of the Bee; and ſo ſhe puts it to her thighs, and rubs one againſt another to faſten it on: and then carrie it home, and make the combs in their Hives.</p>
               <p>The heat of the Bees maketh the waxe ſo warme and ſo pliable, that at the firſt gathering they can worke it and turne it to their purpoſe. Their combs are ſet all upright, beginning at the top, and ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king downe to the bottome. The frame and manner of it is curious, with holes on both ſides of the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:5462:8"/>
combs, many hundreds: yet are they none of them juſt one againſt another, but placed triangular, one againſt three, and that moſt neatly and artificially: which argueth their feeling to be good, for they doe it in the darke.</p>
               <p>They ſeaſon their hony with ſalt water; which (if they be farre from the Sea) they ſucke out of ſinkes or old ditches, and places that encline to ſalt-peter: but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their brood they uſe freſh water:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> them.</note> Therefore it is not amiſſe that you ſet brine, or ſalt water in ſome place neere them, and freſh-water in time of drought.</p>
               <p>They work very diligently, omitting no time to gather in, that is any thing fit, but will abroad, though it be to the hazzard of their lives.</p>
               <p>Their ſight is very cleare, ſpecially farre off,<note place="margin">
                     <p>The ſeverall and quick uſe that they have of all the five ſenſes.</p>
                     <p>Sight.</p>
                  </note> which guides them abroad, and directs them home, though ſometimes in ſtill and mild weather they are three or foure miles off from home: but their ſight is not ſo quick neare hand; for ſometimes they flie againſt you if you come ſuddenly croſſe them, and ſometimes neere the mouth of their Hive, they flie aſide, and miſſe the holes: then up they flie a little further off, and take better view, and ſo fall right.</p>
               <p>Their ſmelling alſo is exceeding quicke,<note place="margin">Smelling.</note> for they will ſent hony a mile from them, and make haſt to it: And by this ſenſe of ſmelling, they find the ſtrange Bees that are not of their own Hive, and ſeeke pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to expell them.</p>
               <p>Their taſte is as active as their other ſenſes;<note place="margin">Taſte.</note> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they make choice of waters, and all other gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings for their uſe and purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Their hearing alſo is very good,<note place="margin">Hearing.</note> and they delight in muſicall ſounds: of which obſervation comes the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:5462:9"/>
ſounding of pannes in ſwarming time: but it uſually doth more hurt than good.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gainſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>g with too ſoone.</note> For if pans be rung, or other troubleſome noiſe till the ſwarme be all out, it cauſeth them to goe back againe, or ſome other di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction it cauſeth among them. Therefore ring not except the ſwarme be flying away; and then make the greateſt ſound you can to prevent it, and throw up duſt, or hogs dung, or cowes dung to diſturbe and trouble them; ſo will they ſettle or goe home again. The Commons are all very laborious and carefull to make proviſions for food and generation: they are very heedfull and obſervant, alſo fearfull of dangers, but marvellous valorous if they apprehend an enemie approaching, or any offenſive creature, and will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely hazzard their lives in defence of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, and ſting other Bees to death that come to robbe or hurt them. Now in ſtinging one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they loſe not their ſtings, for their skinne is ſo dry and thin that their ſpeares come away againe without hurt to themſelves: but in ſtinging thicke and moiſt skinned creatures, they leave their ſtings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them and die,<note place="margin">The nature of envie.</note> for their intrals come forth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with: yet are they ſo furious, that though they die for it, they will doe it: the which the Prophet ſeemes to note, when hee ſaith that <hi>his cruell enemies came about him like Bees;</hi> which may be underſtood, not only in regard of their multitude, but alſo in regard of their great malice and furie, and alſo in regard of their intent, <hi>viz.</hi> to kill and deſtroy: The ſequell of which their furie proved (likewiſe) like this of Bees; they deſtroyed themſelves. And this is the nature of envie, that it will not or cannot be guided by reaſon: from which good Lord deliver us.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:5462:9"/>And thus much of the nature and breeding, comely order and valour of this little creature, which is a fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minine Monarchy, and orderly Common-wealth, conſiſting of an amiable, loving and gentle Queene, and of proper, comely, able, attentive and diligent guard and commanders, with loyall and laborious, provident and valorous Commons: all worthy admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and ſerious obſervation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 4.</hi> Of the getting of Bees, and how to finde and remedy the loſſe of the Queen.</head>
               <p>IN the next place I come to ſet downe my advice to all thoſe that have a deſire to exerciſe, or employ themſelves about Bees. And firſt concerning the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining or getting them.</p>
               <p>Some have received a ſuperſtitious and fooliſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, that if they be bought with mony they will not proſper: but I ſay, let them not be ſtollen, or gotten unjuſtly: for ſtollen goods will not proſper; or if they proſper outwardly, thy conſcience will ſuffer for it, and thou ſhalt have a greater loſſe inwardly than thy gaine will be outwardly. Therefore regard not old wives fables, but get them lawfully, though thou buy them with mony, and then thou mayeſt expect a bleſſing. And for my part I have good ſtore, I thank God, yet I have both bought and ſold to the vallue of a thouſand pound by the yeere, for divers yeeres together.</p>
               <p>Now I ſhould come to ſpeake of removing of Bees, but that I think fit firſt to diſcover a very needful ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:5462:10"/>
and, for ought that ever I have heard, of all men unknowne. And that is, How many, both ſtocks and ſwarmes, doe periſh having loſt their Queene. Which I will here teach how you may both find out, and remedy.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How to know when the Queen is loſt.</note>When you ſee any that have good ſtore of Bees and worke not, then be you ſure that ſomething is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe with them: Either they are annoyed with dead brood: Or diſturbed with ſome enemies, as Ants, or mice, and the like: Or elſe they have loſt their Queene: the which in an evening you may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne by the mornefull noiſe that they will make. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they will mourne, if mice, toads, emmets, or other hurtfull or noyſome thing, be gotten among them: but moſt of all if they have loſt their Queene, roaring and running about the Hive, ſtopping or ſtaying a while, and then begin againe in lamenting manner.</p>
               <p>Then looke under them, and if you eſpie no hatefull thing, bee ſure the Queene is loſt; then beſtirre you to helpe it in time: the which I have done after this manner.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore a Queen.</note>I doe uſually ſave a poore ſwarme at the end of ſummer: and looking over my Bees in winter, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine at the ſpring, I found a good ſtocke that had but few Commons; and looking over them againe, I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved another good ſtock which had loſt their Queen. Then tooke I my poore one, and ſtilled the Bees with ſmoak, &amp; knockt down the Bees and work and all, upon a cloath, and ſo found the Queen, and put her into the middle of that ſtocke which wanted the Queene; and I put the commons to the other which wanted com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons: and ſo both were accepted, the Queen where a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:5462:10"/>
Queene was wanting, and the commons where com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons were wanting: and ſo both my good ſtocks were preſerved; and onely the little poore one (thus for neceſſity) ruinated, which at the beſt was not worth above one ſhilling ſixe pence. I preſerved two good ſtocks thus in the ſpring alſo, which at that time fell to worke preſently, that before had left wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king:<note place="margin">No Drones a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live in winter.</note> and now in both theſe times I found not one Drone living: but in the ſpring I found ſome to bee blown and white in the combs, but not come forth of their cells; which proves plainely the little Bees with the ſtings to be females.</p>
               <p>Now if you find a ſwarme or ſtock in ſummer that hath loſt their Queen,<note place="margin">How to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a ſtock in ſummer that hath loſt the Queene.</note> you may preſerve it by putting a little ſwarme to it: for in putting a Queene where a Queene wants, or common Bees where common Bees are wanting, in both theſe caſes either Queene or commons will bee received: but elſe they will fight and kill one another. But now,<note place="margin">In what caſe Queene or commons will be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</note> if you have no little ſwarme to ſave your ſwarme that hath loſt their Queene, then put that where the Queene is loſt home againe to the old ſtocke: Doe it thus. Knocke it down upon a broad board, and ſet a little board for them, whereon to runne up to the old ſtock.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 4.</hi> Of the time to remove Bees: and placing them to the beſt advantage.</head>
               <p>I Come now to direct concerning removing, ſetting, and ordering of Bees: and firſt of the time of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:5462:11"/>The beſt time to remove your Bees, is in February, or a little before they begin to gather. Indeed you may remove your ſtockes in any of the cold months, (ſo that you bee carefull to carry them upright, and not ſquat or bruiſe them:) but their work is ſtiffeſt and leaſt hony in it about February, and therefore then beſt to carry.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">☞</note>In removing your Bees, alway remember this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, to ſet the ſame ſide foremoſt, that was fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt before; and the ſame place of the Hive for their paſſage out, which they had before you removed them, or elſe you will put their worke out of order.</p>
               <p>If you be driven to remove your ſtockes in warme weather, you muſt remove them the ſpace of a mile or two, or elſe they will goe back to the place whence you did remove them, and ſo many of them will bee loſt and periſh. But ſwarmes are beſt to be removed as ſoone as they are hived, for then they are unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted where they ſtand, and there is nothing then in them which is apt to be bruiſed, or to take harme.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Where and how to place your Bees, after you have remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them.</note>Now when you have them, let them be ſet in the beſt place you have, where they may have a pretty faire flight; and in a ſweet aire, and the ground made cleane before them: the graſſe kept cut, or the ground hard, and ſwept ſometimes. Alſo not neere any deepe water, by the ſpace of ten or twelve ſcore paces, if you can avoid it: for the winde will beat them downe and drowne them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſeat.</note>The beſt ſeat or ſtoole for them is a round board, or ſtone fit to the Hive, onely left an hand breadth wider than the Hive before, for a place for the Bees to alight upon; and ſet it a little leaning forward, for that the raine may runne off, if any be driven or fall
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:5462:11"/>
upon it: yet to keepe them from raine and wet you muſt cover them with boards, if they be ſtraw-hives:<note place="margin">Cover them.</note> or with ſtraw-hackles, if they bee twig-hives: And be ſure to keep them dry, for the wet will decay both the Hive and the Bees worke.</p>
               <p>Set them on a ſingle ſtump, the board faſt nailed; or if on ſtone, et as few ſtumps as will ſet them faſt, and as farre under the ſtoole as may be, to prevent the getting up of mice and other vermine.<note place="margin">Prevent their enemies.</note> Alſo be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to ſet them where no emmets come; for they will get up into the Hive, and ſteale out all the hony, and ſtarve and taint the Bees. But if they come at un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares, then ſhave the ſtumps on which the Bees ſtand, and anoint them round the middle with tarre, which will keepe the Emmets from going up: And throw ſeething water on the emmets, or deſtroy their hill or neſt, if you can find it: and kill the mice with traps or how elſe you can.</p>
               <p>Set your Bees about two foot above the ground, or higher if need bee: let their flight be to the South or Southward, and ſet trees, or other ſhelter not far from them, to breake off the wind; and let not the Sun ſhine hot upon the bare Hives: for their worke will bee in danger to melt. Neither need you to cloath or cover them the more for winter, for the cold hurts them not,<note place="margin">☜ Note this, they muſt not be ſet too hot in the Sunne.</note> ſo they bee defended ſure from the wet: Therefore keepe the Hives whole and cloſe, ſo as two or three Bees may get in and out; for in cold weather, they lie cloſe and ſleep, but ſpend not. Set Goar, Withies, or Palm-trees neere them,<note place="margin">What trees and flowers to ſet neere them.</note> for that is the firſt of their ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therings: Alſo Cherry-trees, Plum and Peare, and any fruit trees: Alſo Roſemary, Time, Burrage, Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gloſs,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:5462:12"/>
Balm, and Violets, Wall and ſtock-gilly-flowers, Rockets, and any other hollow bloome; eſpecially Beanes, Peaſe, Turnep, and ſeed-Cabbage. Alſo they gather much of Buck-wheat and Woad, but both theſe are faint and foggy, and overlade them, and cauſe them to fall downe and periſh. Therefore at ſuch time of the yeere lay ſalt under all your Hives, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in upon the ſtoole, which will quicken your Bees, and put vigour into them, and make them the better able to labour.<note place="margin">When and how to put ſalt under them.</note> Doe the like at other times, when you ſee your ſtocks that have hony in them to be lazy and dull: but thoſe that worke not, being faint for want of hony, muſt bee fed, whether they bee ſtocke or ſwarme; which how to doe I will hereafter ſhow; becauſe many (for want of skill how to feed them) doe it to no purpoſe, and beſides, ſpend more hony in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, by a great deale, than needs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 6.</hi> How to defend your Bees, and preſerve them from their enemies.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Keepe your Bees ſweet and cleane, and alway note and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies they have.</note>AS all Common-wealths are infeſted with ſome e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, ſometimes many, ſometimes fewer: ſo likewiſe is this Common-wealth of Bees. Their great enemies are Hornets, Swallows, Titmice, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins, and the like; beſides Waſpes, and robbing Bees: their leſſer are Emmets, Spiders, &amp;c. which I have ſpoken of before:
<q>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">☞</note>Were it not for the Hornet and the Swallow,</l>
                     <l>Waxe would be as cheape as tallow.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:5462:12"/>Therefore deſtroy the neſts and breeding places of theſe vermine: alſo the creatures themſelves, as oft as you can take them. To take Hornets, ſet lime-twigges before their holes, if you cannot come at their neſts to deſtroy them.</p>
               <p>To take Waſps, ſet glaſſes with wort or water ſweetned with ſweet fruit in it, or a little ſugar melted and diſſolved in the water: but ſweet fruit is the beſt, for feare of drowing the Bees; for they will goe into any thing that hath hony in it.</p>
               <p>Of Emmets and Mice I have ſpoken before: alſo toads, ſnailes &amp; ſpiders are noiſome and hurtful to the Bee. Spiders wil entangle and take them in their webs, and venome them to death, and ſuck out their honie: therefore bruſh downe their webs, and kill them.</p>
               <p>Alſo robbing-Bees are great enemies,<note place="margin">☜ Robbers.</note> and very fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent in the ſpring of the yeere and the fall of the leaſe; which to prevent,<note place="margin">How to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent them.</note> you muſt often prove whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your ſtocks have Bees enough to keep them out. Thoſe ſtocks which have not, you muſt keepe the mouthes of their Hives cloſer, ſo that few may get in.</p>
               <p>If you find that the robbers be too ſtrong for your ſtock, and have made ſome great entrance thereinto, preſently ſtop up that ſtock, though it bee at noon-day: then in the even, ſo that they may ſee to flie, open the hole, and let out the robbers, and be ſure to have ready in your hand ſome white flower, or meale, or lime, or the like, and ſprinkle it on them as they come out, thereby you ſhall know them as they flie: and marke whether they flie to ſome of your owne ſtocks, or to your neighbours; for you ſhall ſee them preſently flie home with the meale on their backes.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:5462:13"/>
Which when you have found, you may thus remedie: Take a long knife or a dagger, &amp; thruſt it into the rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing ſtock about the middle of the Hive, on both ſides: and ſo a little break their work. This will make them leave robbing, and fall to worke to make up their own breaches: and this will doe the robbing ſtockes no hurt, but rather good: for they are commonly the fatteſt Bees which rob, who have enough or too much already; like thoſe that are guided by ſenſe, and ſo cannot tell when they have enough.</p>
               <p>Now after the robbers are thus gone out of your ſtocke, as I have before ſhewed, looke in, and ſee if there be left Bees enow to live: ſhut them in cloſe in the day time for a day, two or three, and let them out about ſun-ſet to take aire: If your ſtocks be full, lay in three or foure little hollow kiskes or quills to let in aire, elſe the full Hives will ſtifle, yet they muſt bee ſo little that a Bee get not through: but if all or the moſt part of your Bees bee gone, if there be not above an handfull of Bees left; then take away the ſtocke quite, and ſave the hony. Better is it to doe ſo than loſe it, for want of Bees to defend it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Trie often whether your ſtocks want Bees.</note>Now in theſe robbing times you muſt try your ſtocks often, whether they want Bees or not; which you may doe by looking in morning and evening: or by knocking on the ſide with a phillip of your fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: if there bee ſtore, they will ruſh a prety while: if few, they will give a little quick ſound; by which you may perceive their quantitie.</p>
               <p>Bees come to decay and be loſt many wayes, as in boiſterous windes, or by faintneſſe, by robbers and fighting, by rotten combs, or dead brood.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:5462:13"/>How you may keepe them in heart and vigour,<note place="margin">Take out the rotten combs and dead Brood.</note> I have already ſhewed; I ſhall now ſhew you how to take off rotten combs, and to take out dead brood, or any other putrefaction.</p>
               <p>You ſhall know when there is dead brood or other putrefaction, by lifting them a little up on one ſide, when it is darke, and put your noſe toward the worke, and ſo ſhall you find an ill favour: then in an evening you may ſtill the Bees, and take it out. That you may ſtill your Bees doe thus:</p>
               <p>Take a coale of fire, and neere the Hive kindle a little dry ſtraw, and caſt upon it a little muck, or green weeds, to keepe it from flaming, and to raiſe ſmoake: then take the infected Hive,<note place="margin">How to ſtill Bees.</note> and hold it over the ſmoak two or three turnes a little while, and the Bees will runne up to the top of the Hive: then turne up the Hive, and you may ſee and ſmell where the dead brood or other putrefaction lieth.</p>
               <p>Some putrefaction ſticks faſt in the cells or holes, and is of a brown or deepe yellowiſh colour, which ſhould have been brood, but came not to perfection.</p>
               <p>Other putrefaction looketh ſomewhat white, and was a brood, but afterward tooke cold, and ſo was chill'd, and periſhed before it came to maturity, and ſo turned to putrefaction: and you may diſcerne it by thruſting your knife into the cells, if otherwiſe you cannot ſee it: and it is eaſie to diſcerne the hony from the putrefaction.</p>
               <p>If the Bees ſtir while you are doing it, quiet them with ſmoake, and ſo drive them up againe: and then take and cut out ſo much worke as you find infected. When there is but little, they can bring it out them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:5462:14"/>
but being much it will trouble them much, and be long in doing: or elſe it will taint and ſtench them up, and make them die, or leave their Hives.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The reaſon why ſmoake rules them.</note>Now the reaſon why ſmoake feares them, and offends them ſo much, is becauſe of the quickneſſe of their ſight and ſmelling: but let it be quickly done, and away, and then they are quickly pleaſed, and come to themſelves againe: but to ſtand continually in a ſmoakie or bad aire they will not thrive: therefore ſet them not neare a Kiln, or any noiſome aire, or where ſmoake may beat downe upon them.</p>
               <p>As concerning rotten or decaied worke, you may know it by feeling; it is criſpy, and of an aſh colour, and without any clammineſſe or wax in it. This you muſt cut off as high as it goeth, for they cannot work to it, but muſt gnaw it off.</p>
               <p>Blackneſſe is no fault, but commeth by the heat of the Bees, and may endure long time notwithſtanding. And thus being carefull and diligent to keepe your Bees ſound and in plight, you may find by Gods bleſſing the profit of your labours in the thriving of your Bees.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 7.</hi> Of ſwarming and hiving your Bees, dreſsing the Hives, and ordering the ſwarmes.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Swarming time.</note>IF the yeere prove warme and kindly, not very wet nor very dry, then may you expect ſwarmes in May: therefore prepare your ſeates and Hives a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that time. If your Hives be old, bee ſure to aire
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:5462:14"/>
them well in the Sunne: but lay them to aire where Hens come not at them, for Bees will not abide the ſent of Hens. If they bee new Hives,<note place="margin">How to dreſſe the hives.</note> remember to make them ſmooth and cleane as you can, by cutting or pulling off the twigges or rinds, which ſtick looſe in the Hive; for elſe the Bees will be troubled to pick it cleane. Concerning the bigneſſe of your Hives, you muſt fit them bigger or leſſer, according to the big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of your ſwarme, or time of the yeere, in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe or backwardneſſe. And rub your Hives with beane, or oake, or willow, or other ſweet leaves: and then ſticke the Hive with a ſticke cleft in foure quarters, and cleft to the upper end within an hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and take off the edges making the ſtick ſmooth and flat: then ſet it to the top of the Hive, and plaſh it foure waies, and ſticke the lower ends faſt into the Hive within ſixe or eight inches of the bottome: and being bent and ſo ſet, they will ſticke faſt. Alſo put two cleft ſticks in the middle, one croſſe the other: let the wood whereof they are made be either withie, or haſell. Then when your ſwarme is come, ſprinkle a little hony or other ſweet thing, as wort, or ſugar diſſolved in faire water, which will make them take the better liking of the Hive.</p>
               <p>As ſoone as the ſwarme is ſetled,<note place="margin">The hiving of Bees.</note> goe preſently to hive it, for feare of riſing, or other comming to it. If it knit or light on the body of a tree, or on ſome ſtiffe thing that cannot bee ſhaken; then with a neat little broome, or little greene bough, ſweepe them into the Hive: or with a thin ſlice of wood, made ſmooth for the purpoſe, ſtrike them in gently: or if you can come to ſet the Hive over them, with greene
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:5462:15"/>
twiggs move or ſtirre them to make them runne up into the Hive: but if they hang on a bough or other place that may be ſhaken, then put your Hive under them, and ſhake them in: and being high on a tree, take a cleane linnen cloath upon your arme, to caſt over the Hive, leſt they flie out in bringing them downe: and being come downe, bee ſure to have a board in readineſſe to ſet them downe upon. Then lay the Hive on the ſide, and turne it up gently, and cover the Hive, all ſave one ſide with the cloth: and that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen ſide, you muſt raiſe, or ſet up with two ſtones or ſtickes, two or three inches high, for the Bees to goe in and out: and if any remaine behind, or flie up, and ſit there againe, then fetch them downe in an empty Hive, and knock them down on the board or cloth, and ſo will they run to their fellowes. And, as I told you before, remember carefully to looke for a Queen.</p>
               <p>If it bee hot weather when you Hive your Bees, then remember to cover or ſhade the Hive with boughs: elſe they will riſe &amp; flie away. Then at night, when they are all within the Hive, carry the ſwarme to the place appointed for them to ſtand in. But ſet them not too neere any new-hived ſwarme, nor yet neere the old ſtock from whence they came, for feare they creep together.</p>
               <p>Now if you chance to obſerve two forward or great ſwarmes comming out together, ſtop up one ſtock with a fine linnen cloath or graſſe, till the other be hived;<note place="margin">What ſwarmes to keepe aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</note> about which you muſt bee quick. Then open the other and let it out, and cover the firſt hived or ſetled ſwarme by hanging a cloath over it: for twenty to one, if the latter riſen ſwarme ſee or
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:5462:15"/>
heare the firſt, but it will to it.</p>
               <p>But now if two little ſwarmes, or late in the yeere,<note place="margin">And what to unite.</note> riſe and goe together, that is beſt of all, ſo that they agree and doe not fight. Yea if they goe not together, it is beſt to put them together: which you may doe after this manner.</p>
               <p>When they are both hived, take the firſt, and ſet it on a board, and ſpred a cleane cloth upon the board, if the board be not broad enough, and knock the laſt ſwarme downe on the end of the board, by the firſt: which being ſet up two or three inches on the ſide, next to that which you have knockt downe, they will of themſelves run to the other ſwarme: and in their running up to the other ſwarm, you may ſee the Queen, which you muſt take away; ſhe will not ſting: and you may put her into the ſtocke which ſhee came from, unleſſe you have any other ſwarme or ſtocke which wanteth a Queene, unto which you may put her. Thus you may unite ſwarmes, and ſo you ſhall have none little or poore.</p>
               <p>But if notwithſtanding all your care two great or forward ſwarmes doe goe together, which you thinke are too bigge (for a competent number is the beſt) you may devide or part them thus:</p>
               <p>Firſt ſtill the Bees with ſmoak, as is before ſhewed:<note place="margin">How to divide great ſwarmes that are gone together.</note> then having another Hive ready trimed and dreſt, ſet it by upon a board teeled, or ſet up a little on one ſide: then beat or knock downe ſome of the Bees where two are gone together, and in running or going to the empty Hive, one Queen will be found, which you muſt put to the empty Hive; and knock Bees out of the other, till you have a competent num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber:
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:5462:16"/>
but be very carefull that the Queens be divided too, or elſe the commons will together againe, or periſh for want of a Queene.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The cauſe of fighting among ſwarmes.</note>Thus alſo you may make to agree two little ſwarmes which goe together, or are put together, by taking away one Queene, and make them leave figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, which otherwiſe will diſ-agree; for if there bee fighting or diſtraction among ſwarmes, it is for want of a Queene; or having two Queenes they will ſtrive which ſhall governe till one be killed, and then they will be at peace.</p>
               <p>Alſo when you put two little ſwarmes together, it is good to ſprinkle ſtrong beere, or ſtrong ale a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, to make them all of one ſent; ſo can they not find out one ſort from another, but be all as one and agree.</p>
               <p>In the next place remember to heed your ſwarmes, that they flie not away when the hony dewes fall (for many hony dewes doe fall in gloomie weather:) and in ſuch times they may chance ſtay a while, and work in their Hives,<note place="margin">How to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent ſwarmes from flying away.</note> and yet afterward leave all and bee gone into the woods; where they from the Oaken leaves can gather more freely and readily: which to prevent, be ſure to feed them with hony, by putting in a cane or kiske of hony into their Hives every morning, till they have gotten ſome ſtore, and have ſome proviſions in their Hives, which may give them content at home, and ſo keepe them from ſtraying abroad.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>How to feed Bees.</head>
                  <p>Note this by the way, that Bees are not to bee fed
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:5462:16"/>
in the winter, but in the ſpring and ſummer, in cold or wet or over-dry weather; when hony is not to be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered abroad, then feed your ſwarmes,<note place="margin">Times to feed in, are cold or wet or over-dry.</note> elſe may they ſtarve, or pine, or be out of heart, and not able to work.</p>
                  <p>To feed them doe thus: Take a kiske or cane that is hollow, and cut it ſo that you leave a knot at each end of the kiske: let the kiske be eight or twelve inches long, and in bigneſſe anſwerable to the number of Bees in the ſwarme or ſtocke that you feed. Then cut open and make the kisk hollow on the upper-ſide, and there powre in the hony, and put it under the Hive: knit a ſtring to the end of the kiske, to pull it out of the Hive: ſo may you put it in or pull it out quite, without raiſing of it. Thus you may feed your poore ones, at the Spring, when you find your ſtocks without hony.</p>
                  <p>But if (notwithſtanding all your diligence) you have ſome poore ones at the end of the yeere, then if you take any ſtock, ſave ſome hony combs to feed with, at the Spring: then in the Spring, when you ſee them gather, (if they want food) you may put in thoſe preſerved hony combs: which you may doe after this manner:</p>
                  <p>Firſt ſtill the Bees with ſmoake (but not too early in the morning, leſt they take harme by the cold aire:<note place="margin">A very ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved way of feeding Bees.</note>) then turn them up, and take out a combe neere the Bees, wherein is no hony, and in ſtead thereof, place the hony-combe, and pin it in with thin ſpleets thruſt through the Hive to faſten it: and ſet it ſo that the Bees may goe between the combs: and this they will take for their owne, and be content to ſtay. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, when hony is to bee had in the fields, they
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:5462:17"/>
will flie away, if they have none of their owne.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>How to take Bees that you find in a Tree.</head>
                  <p>But now if notwithſtanding all your diligence a ſwarme happen to flie into the woods, and get into a hollow tree, or if you chance to finde a ſwarme in a tree; if the tree be not your owne, firſt get leave of the owner, and then take it out: which you may doe after this manner.</p>
                  <p>Cut an hole a little above the place where the Bees lye, and another a little below them, and ſet a prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red hive over the uppermoſt hole, and make a ſmoak without flame in the under hole, putting it in and out too and fro; and ſo you ſhall make the Bees to runne up into the hive: then put a cloth over the hive, and tye it round with a line, and ſo bring it home.</p>
                  <p>If the Bees be newly gone in, they will the ſooner be gotten out; but if they have bin there ſome time, and have gotten good ſtore of proviſion in the tree be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you finde them, then they will hardly and with much adoe leave it; then your beſt way will be to cut it off: which if it bee but an arme of a tree, is eaſily done; or if in the body of a tree, where you can come at it, cut above it and below it; and being cut (a rope being firſt faſtened about it) let it downe as gently as you can, for feare of bruiſing and ſquatting: then ſtop the holes, or tye a cloth about them, and bring them home, and naile a board at the top to keepe out the water: then ſet them in your garden, or ſome other convenient place.</p>
                  <p>But now if there be no way to cut it downe or to ſave it, then when it is fulleſt of hony take it: which
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:5462:17"/>
you may doe after this manner. Cut an hole under it, and take matches of brimſtone, ſet them on fire and put under them, and ſtop the hole to keepe in the aire and vapour of the brimſtone: and this will kill them ſtone dead. So may you take out the hony and waxe, and make uſe of it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>How and when to drive full and fat ſtockes.</head>
                  <p>If the yeere bee ſuch that many hony-dewes fall, and your ſtockes prove ſo fat that they lie out, and will not ſwarme, then about the middeſt of July drive ſome of the fatteſt: which you may doe thus: In an evening take the fat and full Hive, and ſet it upon a big joyned ſtoole or ſome other hollow frame, with the mouth upward: then take a prepared Hive, being ſprinkled with hony, and ſet over it, and bind a cloth round about them, to keepe the Bees in: then knock or rap the under Hive, to make the Bees goe up to the empty Hive. This doe often to move them and diſturb them to make them run upward: and if you can, open or make an hole in the top of the under Hive; and with a litle ſmoak under them, you may drive them upward, and ſo let them ſtand all night; and in the morning if you by knapping, perceive any Bees to remaine ſtill in the under Hive, then doe ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine till all or the moſt part be gone up: then take the upper Hive, and ſet it where the full ſtock ſtood: and take out the combs of the driven Hive, and put them into a pan or kettle: and in taking out the combs, ſhake or bruſh off the Bees (if any remaine) ſo will they goe to their old place to the new prepared Hive.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:5462:18"/>Experience will make you more perfect and readie in theſe things. Be not fearefull, but patient and gentle, and in caſe of neceſſity, over-rule your Bees by ſmoak, and ſo you may doe about them whatſoever is fit: but if by chance you are ſtung by them,<note place="margin">What to doe when you are ſtung by the Bees.</note> firſt pull out the ſting preſently, then wet your finger often with ſpet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and apply to the place, and keepe it wet and coole in the aire: and then it will not ſmell. Alſo if you rub the place with Mary-golds, or hony, or S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> 
                     <hi>Johns</hi> wort, is a good remedy unto ſome.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>How to make Bees ſwarme.</head>
                  <p>If ſome ſtocks hang out ſomewhat long, and are not willing to ſwarme; to provoke them to ſwarme, doe thus: Raiſe up the Hive on that ſide where the Bees lie out, about three or foure inches high, and with a little ſmoake, and alſo by ſtirring and moving them, make them goe up into their Hive: then let downe the Hive cloſe againe to the ſtoole, and rub the place where the Bees lay, with elder, May-weed, or hemlock, ſo will they abide in, and in ſhort time ſwarme. But if this will not ſerve to make them ſwarme, then drive thoſe that are full and fat, as is before ſhewed.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:5462:18"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 8.</hi> Wherein firſt is taught how to chuſe for ſtore: Secondly, how to helpe them that have too little, and take from them that have too much: Thirdly, ſignes of the firſt ſwarming: Fourthly, how to recover Bees that are chilled with cold.</head>
               <p>FOr choice of the beſt for ſtore, alway keepe them that have the faireſt and the eveneſt work, neither too fat nor too leane, and full of Bees. If a ſwarme bee very fat, chooſe rather to keep an old one of a middle waight, than that fat one; chooſe one about three pecks or a buſhell waight, and not above: for if their combs be all full of hony, then they have no where to breed, and will not ſwarme, and may periſh for want of Bees.</p>
               <p>Now if your Bees bee too fat,<note place="margin">Feed the lean, and take from them that are too fat.</note> and all their combs full of hony; then at the ſpring of the yeere ſtill your Bees, and cut off the combs two or three in the middle a foot high, ſo will they worke new, and breed: And if then you have any too poore and light, then feed them as is before ſhewed.</p>
               <p>Now in chooſing your Bees for ſtore, if you find that their work is crumbling, or criſping into ſmall crumbs, as big as a great pins-head, then be ſure thoſe Bees are faulty, or robbers, or ſtrange Bees haunt them, or they diſlike ſomething. And if your Bees bee kindly to ſwarme, you may keepe them long, though old and black, for blackneſſe is no fault ſo long as they bee ſound. If a ſtocke ſwarme, and ſtand to health, and ſo hold out healthfull for three yeeres, I have knowne ſuch ſtand eighteen or twenty yeeres.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:5462:19"/>
                  <note place="margin">Signes of the firſt ſwarme.</note>Now to direct you to know the firſt ſwarming of your Bees, the ſignes are theſe. The males or Drones will commonly play forth three or foure daies, or more, before they ſwarme; and the Bees will play ſwarme-play; and ſometimes you may ſee the Queen come out and in before ſwarming. Concerning the ſignes of ſecond ſwarms, I have before ſhewed by cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Bees; and alſo how to put the late little ſwarmes together, or elſe put them back into the ſtocke to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the ſtock, which elſe may dye for want of Bees.</p>
               <p>Now if notwithſtanding all your care and diligence ſome prove light, as under the weight of eighteen or twenty one pounds weight, then when they have done gathering, cloſe them up faſt with cow-dung and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes mixt together, or lime and haire, which mice cannot gnaw,<note place="margin">
                     <p>Set poore ſtocks into the houſe in win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
                     <p>Bees eate not in winter.</p>
                  </note> and ſet them (ſtoole and all) into ſome cold dry place of your houſe or barne, where they may be little ſenſible of the change or alteration of the ayre; for as long as they ſtirre not they eate not. And this is the reaſon that they may not bee fed in cold winter, but onely when they gather, at the ſpring or ſummer cold. Alſo keepe your Hives cloſe in win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, by putting ſtones at the mouth of the Hive, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent mice from going in; and open them wider, or ſhut them up cloſer in the ſpring time, according as the weather proves hotter or colder, and according to the ſtrength or weakeneſſe of your ſtocks.</p>
               <p>Alwaies in ſnowie weather remember to ſhut up your Bees cloſe in ſunſhine, or elſe they will out, and be drowned or chilled. And ſometimes in cold ſprings a poore ſwarme may bee ſtarved or benum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med before you are aware. I once found two or
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:5462:19"/>
three ſo benummed that none of them were able to ſtirre, but ſat as dead Bees.<note place="margin">How to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver chilled Bees.</note> Then made I an indifferent big fire before them, and tooke them off their ſeares, and turned them open againſt the fire, and ſo the warmth recovered them, and made them move: then I ſprinkled hony in among them, and ſet them up, and laid ſalt on their ſtooles, within the Hives: and then they came forth preſently, and went to worke: ſo then I fed them a little every day, and recovered them.</p>
               <p>Alſo you muſt remember to bee very carefull in keeping hoggs, or horſes,<note place="margin">Be ſure to keep cattell from them.</note> or any cattell from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming neere them to trouble them. Once I knew a good Nag ſtung to death by them. But if any trouble or diſturbance chance, and they prove very angry and cruell, and unruly, then make a great ſmoake among them, and ſo they will quickly bee quiet and ſtill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
               <p>Many things more I could have ſhewed concerning Bees, but theſe I have here delivered are things of uſe, and moſt needfull to be knowne.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>How to take Bees.</head>
                  <p>Now when God hath bleſſed your labours, and ſent you ſtore, you may receive the benefit of your labour, by ſelling or taking ſome. And alwayes if any be over fat, and their combs all filled with hony, be ſure to take them: which to doe, and how to make and order your hony and waxe, is ſhewed in the next chapter.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:5462:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 9.</hi> Of making hony, mead, and wax.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How to take Bees.</note>TO take your Bees doe thus: untwiſt an old rope or cord, and of the ſeverall liches, cut peeces ſix or eight inches in length: then melt Brimſton in a pan or potſheard, and dip the peeces of cord into it, and wet it round as a candle: then take ſome little tub, or deepe bowle, or elſe dig an hole in the ground, and lay two ſticks over it, and then light or kindle your match, and then put them on a ſhort candle-ſtick, or a peece of clay, and ſet it into the bowle or hole, and ſet the ſtock of Bees over it, and keep in the aire round about the Hive with an old cloth, and ſo the ſteeme or vapour of the brimſton will kill the Bees ſtone dead:<note place="margin">How to make hony.</note> then take out the combs, and bruſh off the Bees, if any hang on, and breake out the dead brood, if any be: then put all thoſe combs that have hony in them, into a pan or kettle, and bruiſe them together: and ſtraine it through a thin cloth-bag: or if you will have your hony very fine, let it run through a ſieve with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cruſhing. Now if your hony were gathered on good land, in a good ſoile, it will need no warming: but if on courſe or clay land, you muſt ſet it on the fire when it is ſtrained, and make it twice blood-warme; then ſtirre it well, and put it into the veſſell where you intend to keepe it; and after a while ſcum it, and it will be candied.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">Mead.</note>How to make Mead.</head>
                  <p>Now when you have taken as much hony out of your combs or pulſe as you can doe, then waſh your puls with water made blood-warme, and make your Mead with that. And if you deſire to have your Mead
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:5462:20"/>
very good and ſtrong, make it ſo full of the hony, that it will beare a hen-egge ſwimming as broad as a ſixe pence on the top: then ſet it over the fire, and boyle it well, and take the ſcum clean off; then ſet it a clearing into a kive or tub, two or three daies till it be cleare; and then draw it off from the lees or grounds, and put it up into a veſſell; but ſtop it not too cloſe, for the ſtrength of it will teare the veſſell in peeces. Alſo if you will, you may put in a bag of ſpices thereinto in boyling.</p>
                  <p>But now,<note place="margin">Metheglin.</note> how to make metheglin I purpoſe not to teach you; for it is part of my preſent trading: both hony and metheglin have an excellent vertue for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny cures; being moderately taken they doe remedy many diſeaſes.<note place="margin">The good uſe of hony, mead and metheglin</note> They are eſpecially good againſt a cold conſumption, or cold watery ſtomacke, as alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt divers other both inward &amp; outward diſeaſes.</p>
                  <p>Alſo there may bee admirable Baths made of it, and ſtrange cures have beene done therewith: it is proved in my own experience, in ſalves both for old and new wounds, that both wax and hony are very ſoveraigne.<note place="margin">Aches and itches.</note> I have holpen aches and ſtrong itches in Bathes made of hony.</p>
                  <p>Once I had a friend had ſuch a foule itch that hee was like a Leper: then I tooke an empty wine Caske, call'd a Pipe, and tooke out one head, and made a liquor of water and hony, making it pretty ſtrong with the hony, and heat it as hot as my friend could indure to ſtand in it, and put it into the Pipe, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to ſtand in it up to his neck a pretty while; and this he did three daies one after another, and was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered as cleare as ever. The like experience for aches. If the Bath bee a little renewed with a little
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:5462:21"/>
hony every day, it is the better.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>How to make wax.</head>
                  <p>In making wax, you muſt put both your pulſe and dry combs together into a kettle, and put an indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent quantity of water thereunto, and make it boyle on the fire: then take a thin cloth bag very ſtrong, or a haire bag, and cruſh it as hard as you can; and have ſeething water ready by you to put into the bag, and to caſt on the outſide of the bag, and wind it up cloſe, and cruſh and ſqueeſe it hard. This doe three or foure times, and the wax will come cleane away. Then let it ſtand in the keelar or bowle till it be cold; and then take up all the wax from the water, and melt it again with a little water in the bottom to keep the veſſell from burning; and being melted put it into a pan or veſſell, of what ſize you think fit to make your cake or tren of wax: but firſt annoint the veſſell by the ſides with a little hony, or butter, and ſo the wax will come clean off.</p>
                  <p>The ſingular uſe of wax in ſalves and chirurgery, for cures both within and without, and for uſe in making candles for ſweet and dainty burning, and the divers other uſes, is well known: therefore I ſay no more, but praiſe the Lord for all his marvellous benefits.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Whether women may govern.</note>And now, may there be any further uſe or appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation made of this knowledge? Yes ſurely: for the moſt wiſe God hath founded all his works in wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and ſet them forth for us to make uſe of.</p>
                  <p>How then ſhall I apply it? Why I raiſe this Quere: This is a feminine Monarchie, the females governe: But it is lawfull for women to govern in a common-wealth?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> Yes, in ſome caſes: that is, firſt, when the male
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:5462:21"/>
ſex is wanting; or ſecondly, otherwiſe diſabled by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall diſability: as here; nature not having enabled the male to governe, the female doth it. And ſurely God hath given this inſtance in nature, to confirme this truth: other inſtances we have even in ſacred writ, as in <hi>Debora</hi> the Propheteſſe: the Queene of the South that came to heare King <hi>Salomon:</hi> Queene <hi>Candace</hi> of Aethiopia, and others. But ſee this royall Queen of Bees, how qualified; ſhe is faire, comely, loving, harmeleſſe, gentle, peaceable, yea a vigilant Queen, a royall emblem of government. See alſo the care, labour, diligence, providence and proviſion, watchfulneſſe, valour, and loyalty, of this common-wealth. How would that common-wealth flouriſh, where the members joyning in ſuch unanimity, ſhould all (ſetting aſide private gaine) aime wholly at the publike weale; and in defence thereof eſteem nothing too deare to beſtow, no not their lives? as it is with theſe poore flies, who will reſolutely hazzard their lives for the generall good. See alſo their policy too, in keeping and preſerving the ſeed royall, and admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting but one to governe, to prevent contention and domeſtick broyles. A rare pattern, and indeed a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Hieroglyphick of a well governed Republick.</p>
                  <p>But to deſcend lower: May the female from this example, urge a power of government in private houſes and families? Let me anſwer in a diſtick or two of our Engliſh Maro, (whoſe baptized muſe hath clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed vertue in a more pleaſing habit, that ſo ſome may fall in love with her, if not for her owne ſake, yet at leſt may come to the ſight of her beauty in that poetick garbe.)</p>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:5462:22"/>
                     <l>Ill thrives that hapleſſe family that ſhowes,</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Quarles.</note>A cocke that's ſilent, and an hen that crowes.</l>
                     <l>I know not which live more unnaturall lives,</l>
                     <l>Obeying husbands, or commanding wives.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>But I wiſh there were not too many of theſe: But how may it be remedied? Perſwaſions, inſtructions, and wholſome words from the husband may doe much, if God add his bleſſing. Take that incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble loving example of our Saviour toward his Church, ſet forth by S. <hi>Paul, And remember alway that your labour is not in vaine, for the woman is the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the man.</hi> And let me add, that a vertuous woman will do thee good and not hurt all the daies of her life.</p>
                  <p>But what if ſhe be ſtubborn and ſelfe-will'd, ſo that ſhe is nothing the better for thy paines? I anſwer: It was thy hard hap to meet with her; and though thou doe her no good, yet know that thy labour is with the Lord, and thy reward with the Almightie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q</hi> But may not a woman govern in the houſe? Yes, if God hath made her able: for ſhe was created to bee an helpe: and eſpecially in her husbands abſence or weakneſſe ſhe ought to perform her beſt therein: and ſometimes with meekneſſe (remembring her ſex,) to adviſe her husband: for ſomtimes two heads are better than one, <hi>&amp; plus vident oculi quam oculus.</hi> And a wiſe woman will obſerve the waies of the family, &amp; ſee to their labours &amp; emploiments with diligence &amp; watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, and bring up her children in the feare &amp; nurture of the Lord, &amp; in all things be as carefull as thy ſelfe; and all little enough in this age, wherein both ſervants and children are (many of them) very unruly and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toward; and there is worke enough to keepe them in order. More might be ſaid, but this is moſt pertinent:
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:5462:22"/>
and perhaps ſome of this may bee cenſured by ſome. For what is ſo well done but may bee amended? or what can any man doe but ſome will calumniate? But my poore endevours are entended to profit the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and well minded. And ſo I end this little tract or direction, for the ordering of this little, yet profitable Common-wealth of Bees.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 10.</hi> Bees and women compared.</head>
               <p>OUt of the experience of ruling Bees may be lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned how to rule moſt women: for there is ſome reſemblance between them.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>So are wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</head>
                  <item>1. Bees are very ſenſible and apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of any good or evill that is for them or againſt them.</item>
                  <item>2. Bees are very teachy and paſſionate.</item>
                  <item>3. Bees if they be well governed, and kept in good order, are very induſtrious, but let them be out of order, or ill hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and there comes no good of them, but hurt and trouble.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. Therefore to anſwer their ſenſes which are ſo quick &amp; apprehenſive, let them not apprehend or ſee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny evill from you by your example, but alwaies good.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For their paſſions, overcome them by reaſons and love: But ſome are ſo paſſionate, that reaſon cannot rule; others ſo ſottiſh and ſluttiſh, that they cannot bee ordered, or altred from what they are: for the will is more froward than the minde is ignorant. But if you can win a woman thus, ſhe may be both profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and a comfort.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="book">
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:5462:23"/>
            <head>THE SECOND BOOKE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 1.</hi> In this ſecond Booke is ſhewed the cauſe, together with the cure of blaſted wheat: alſo of rye, hops, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE blaſting of Wheat commeth two wayes: 1. Either by windes: 2. Or by mildewes. The blaſting by winde happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in our country but ſeldome; and for this kinde of blaſting I confeſſe I know no cure: for the winde bloweth where it liſts, without poſſible re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance from any mans power. That which I ſhall here ſpeake of, is that blaſting which comes by mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dew, threatned from God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.22. It is an affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction which by our ungratefulneſſe we provoke God to ſend upon us; a ſinne that deſerves puniſhment, not onely by depriving us of the food of our bodies, but of our ſoules too: yet upon repentance God hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to take away our ſinnes, and to cure our ſickneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; for hee hath a ſalve for every ſore, if wee had hearts to ſeeke it of him who is able to give.</p>
               <p>Now for this mildew, it is a fine thin ſweet dew when it falleth; no dew or water in the earth is ſo thin, that I know of: yet if it lye till the ſunne or heat come upon it, or windes dry it, then it becomes clam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, ſtiffe, and binding: but the worſt effect that it hath, is upon wheat and hopps.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:5462:23"/>It falls commonly in the warmeſt and ſtilleſt wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; it is exhaled or drawn up by the ſunne out of the flowers, and from ſweet things or ſweet places of the earth: and it is moſt frequent in the height of ſummer and warme weather, eſpecially a little before wheat harveſt: ſo that wheat is taken by it when it is full corne in the eare, and the ſtraw is dry and beginneth to change white. It falleth ſometimes in the night, ſometimes in the day, but moſt of all in cloudy, miſty, and gloomy weather. The which to find out, keepe Bees, and they will be your intelligencers.</p>
               <p>If it fall in the night, they will out to gather as ſoone as day is light; or if it fall by day, they will abroad to gather, though it fall faſt, and as big as a pretty raine. Therefore when you ſee them flie thus early and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently, bee ſure there is a ſweet dew fallen: then make haſt before the Sun or drineſſe commeth on it, and get helpe, and away into your wheat, and with a line or rope run over your wheat as faſt as may bee, one in one furrow, and another in another furrow a land, two or three diſtance, as you can well reach, one at one end, and the other at the other end of the cord or pole: and the leaſt touch or wagging will ſhake it off, it is ſo exceeding thin when it is new fallen. Yet if you have time and helpe, it were good that you went backward as well as forward, to make ſure worke. But if you let the dew alone, it will ſtick faſt when heat or drineſſe commeth on it, and ſo in time will ſet your wheat, ſo that no moiſture or nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can come out of the root into the eare, and then your corne ſhrinkes in the eare for want of nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. This dew will in time ſtick faſt, and become
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:5462:24"/>
clammy, and bind like Turpentine or Bird-lime, firſt ſtraked on the ſtraw, and within a while all black o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and round about the ſtraw: while the wheate is greene, and that there is moiſture in the ſtraw, ſo long the mildew doth no hurt; ſo likewiſe when the corn is hard and dead ripe in the eare, it is then paſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: ſo that the greateſt hurt is done betweene the time that it beginneth to change colour, and the full ripening; and if you be careleſſe and negligent in this time, be ſure your wheat will be dryed up with the Sunne, and ſhrunk in the eare, and blaſted like <hi>Phara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oh's</hi> leane kine, and his leane eares of corne in Aegypt, nothing but huske; which by Gods bleſſing, and your ſmall paines and diligence, you may prevent. Some have ſleighted and contemned this weake meanes for a while, as <hi>Naaman</hi> the Syrian did the advice of the Prophet <hi>Eliſha,</hi> who bade him waſh in Jordan and be cleane; but after better conſideration have made uſe of it, and found the profit and benefit, and were thankfull for it.</p>
               <p>The mildew is alſo to be perceived upon the oake leaves ſhining and ſweet: but having your intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers at home, you need not ſeek abroad.</p>
               <p>Concerning the blaſting by wind, and cold or hot ayre, it is not very frequent in our Countrey, thanks be to God: yet rye and fruit is ſometimes blaſted by ſome of theſe, and hops very often by the mildew; therefore when this dew falleth, ſhake your hop-poles, and with a gentle wand beat off this dew from the leaves, and if it bee not too much labour, waſh it off alſo by throwing water, if you ſee that it will not come off with ſhaking: for if it ſtick on and continue
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:5462:24"/>
there, you ſhall ſee wormes and bobs breed and ſtick there, and ſo ſpoile your hops, and they will be low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey and filthy, and much impayred, if not all loſt. Now if you bee diligent and watchfull herein, you may, by Gods bleſſing, receive double and trebble or greater recompence of your paines, and preſerve a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance which the former ages have loſt.</p>
               <p>Rye and fruit is blaſted with the wind, or in cold or hot aire, and in froſts, therefore I think it were good in froſts to ſhake off the dew, before the ſun ſhineth upon it, or to make ſome ſmoake or ſmolder to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the coldneſſe of the aire, (taking heed alway that your fire doe no harme.) Now the time wherein fruit and rye are blaſted, is moſt commonly in the blowing of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 2.</hi> The reaſon why this knowledge hath ſo long laine hid, and now diſcovered.</head>
               <p>EVerie thing hath an appointed time (ſaith the wiſe man in his <hi>Eccl.</hi>) and God hath made every thing beautifull in his time. And this is the very reaſon why this knowledge hath laine ſo long hid, and now com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be knowne: for in theſe latter ages, the world is exceeding populous, and our mother Earth (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther now grown weaker in her age, <hi>&amp; ad ruinam ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gens,</hi> I will not here diſpute the queſtion: but) ſcarce able to yeeld food for thoſe that live on her: in this time I ſay, hath God revealed this knowledge. For he taketh care of, and provides for all his creatures; and as he ſent the diſeaſe, ſo hee can ſhew the cure: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:5462:25"/>
let us learn to aſcribe it all unto him, and to give him the praiſe: for he diſpenſeth all his gifts wiſely, where and when hee ſees need. And doe wee not ſee how in this age God hath ſhewed the art of liming, &amp; other manuring of land, to the wonderfull improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof? Beſides, ſince our Woods failed, the fewell of coale, peat, turfe, and the like, hath beene found. The which let us neither deſpiſe nor neglect, but embrace, and give the all-wiſe and ever-loving God his due praiſe and glory therefore.</p>
               <p>But what if for all this <hi>Thomas</hi> will not beleeve? Let him ſtrive with himſelfe, and enforme himſelfe, and come to his fellow Diſciples, and conferre with them. But let him not looke now for any ſpeciall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation: time and experience may convince him of the truth of that which at the firſt ſight appeares fabulous.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 3.</hi> Of the cauſe and remedy of ſmutty wheat.</head>
               <p>I Come now to ſet downe my opinion concerning the cauſes and the remedy of ſmutty wheat, ſo much as I know; becauſe in this, wherein I am not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perfect, I will not be peremptory: but when I have attained the full knowledge, I entend alſo (God willing) to publiſh it.</p>
               <p>The cauſe I conceive to be this: a defect or failing in nature, 1. Of the ſeed: or 2. Of the land: or 3. Of both; but rather of the wheat: for as all things are of the earth, ſo to the earth they decline and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne: and things that are beſt decay, die, and putrifie,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:5462:25"/>
and ſo become the worſt and baſeſt of all: and when they are at their height, or greateſt ſtrength and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, then they ſoone returne and decay. I apply it to my matter in hand. Wee ſee moſt men will make choice of the faireſt, freeſt, plumpeſt, and waightieſt wheat for ſeed, and they think that they doe well in it: but obſerve it better, and make other trials of it, and ſee what will come of it. Is the fatteſt Bull or Oxe, or the fatteſt Cow, the beſt to keepe? It may for a yeere or thereabouts, but when they are fallen in their fleſh, will they ſo eaſily riſe againe? Or will not the poorer cattell ſooner riſe, and make the beſt improvement, eſpecially if the poore cattell come out of a meane or weake paſture, and are put in a good and full paſture, and the fat are juſt contrary? Doth the full growne tree or plant grow higher and better, or doth it not rather decay, after it hath attained it's perfection? But to inſtance in my owne Element: Doe the fatteſt ſtocks of Bees prove better, or the moſt fruitfull? No ſurely, I find that good midling ſtocks, that are mending, prove beſt, and ſwarme oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt: and the very fat ones prove leaner, and ſometimes die, but ſeldome ſwarme. So I take it to be in this caſe: when wheat is at the beſt, it doth ſoone decay and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come worſe, yea naught and worſe than naught. You ſhall ſee it come up in great plenty, blades enough, and ſtraw enough, and ſhoots the eare, and is corne in the eare; but ſuddenly it periſheth &amp; dieth in the eare, and becommeth naught; yea duſt, and vile duſt, worſe than the earth, and of no uſe, but putrified, dead and gone. You may ſee it at a ſtand, and dead in the eare; the eare gaping and ſtaring, much differing from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:5462:26"/>
that hath life and vigour in it. And if the land be not in very good heart, much of your wheat will be thus ſpoiled; and the more that comes up, and the greater bulk, the more will periſh and become blacke, and will ſoile all your good wheat in the threſhing, and will make it blacke at the ends: and it hath a dampe and faintiſh ſmell with it, and I thinke, is not wholſome to eate; therefore picke or leaſe it out of the ſheafe before you threſh it, or elſe you had need waſh it well, and drie it after it is threſh't, before you eate it. Therefore when your wheat is very faire, plumpe, and waighty, uſe that rather to ſpend in your houſe; for it yeelds more and better flowre: but for ſeed chuſe a middle ſize, not ſo great, nor yet of the ſmalleſt rank, but a middle ſort.</p>
               <p>Another reaſon to prove that wheat when it is at the beſt decayes ſooneſt, you ſhall ſee in this experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment following. Sow of this wheat the next yeere, whether it bee waſhed or not waſhed, yet it will bee very ſmutty; whereas if you ſow leaner or a mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling wheat on the ſame land, and the ſame ſeaſon, yea that very day, and yet the one will turne ſmutty, and the other will not; which proveth that the plump and fulleſt wheat, being at it's height and period, returnes, decayeth, and commeth to nought: (Oh the fleeting and fading eſtate of all, yea of the beſt earthly things!)</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>How to helpe, and to prevent, and keepe wheat, that it ſmut or decay not.</head>
                  <p>I have by ſome little experience, found that there is much helpe in the choice of the wheat, and ordering
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:5462:26"/>
of the land for the ſeed: but moſt of all in adding vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor and help to the ſeed which is ſowne, by ſteeping it in and with a certaine ingredient, before it be ſowne, which keepeth it from decay and ſmut. And of this I purpoſe hereafter to publiſh ſomewhat more, when I have gained the certaine experience by further triall. In the meane time prove ſome of what I have here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, and make choice of your ſeed, not the faireſt and plumpeſt, but the hardeſt, and a midling graine, neither fatteſt nor leaneſt.</p>
                  <p>Or if you think good to trie this experiment, ſow the ſame day, and on the ſame land, a little of the plumpeſt faireſt ſeed that you can get, and ſome other of a midling hardie graine: and you ſhall ſoone obſerve the difference: eſpecially if your land be ſomewhat weake, and a little out of heart, the difference will the ſooner ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
